# **Marie-Theres Riegler**

Entrepreneurial consultant and lecturer with background in strategy, business and user-/customer experience with 10+ years' experience of driving transformational change in a range of industries and markets. Highly knowledgeable in the fashion and luxury industry. Always striving to achieve the best results and inspire team members and students. Well-versed in business strategy, research, stakeholder-management, customer experience, analysis and developing strategic action plans. A gifted communicator with excellent relationship-building and problem-solving abilities. Passionate about creating products and services, supporting businesses, sharing knowledge and experiences. Lifelong learner.

## **Work Experience**

## 2022-07

#### **Guest Lecturer**

Sotheby's Institute of Art **Topic: Future-proofing Luxury** MA Luxury Business

#### 2022-02 - 2022-07

## Senior Strategist – Freelance

**AKQA London** 

- Led the strategy development, workshops and research for transformational business and rebranding projects.
- Worked with C-suite clients from FMCG, entertainment, fashion, luxury, sports.

#### 2019-10 - Current

## Visiting Lecturer

European College of Business and Management – in partnership with LJMU and University of South Wales

Modules: Fashion Media and Communication (BA) Holistic Retail Design (MA)

- Developed course materials and assignments for on-and offline lectures, catering to different group sizes.
- Lead inspired seminars and encouraged students to learn new skills (e.g. user research, customer experience, product and idea development).
- Utilized innovative methods of instruction, including video, interactive class activities, field trips and discussions to deliver course material in an engaging way.
- Assessment of students' learning and performance.

## 2014-09 - Current

## Freelance Consultant (Strategy, Customer Exp., Comms)

Client Excerpt: AKQA, DHL, A globally renown FMCG company, Zalando, Decoded Fashion, AVMM, #SR

- Conducted trend- and cultural research to inform new product launches
- Helped clients improve their usability and increase user engagement based on data and complimentary research.
- Created actionable recommendations for corporate clients in the field of UX and CX.
- Successfully conducted website content audits.
- Supported clients in identifying and solving problems throughout the customer journey.
- Identified appropriate channels and target customer segmentation for businesses in different industries.
- Studied demographic data to determine optimal targets, competitor offerings and tactics for differentiation.
- Continuously developed experiential ideas based on current and future
- Offered user- and data-driven recommendations aligned with overall company strategies and prioritized process improvement initiatives for a variety of clients.
- Analyzed and wrote business plans, identified inefficiencies in existing processes, and tracked performance improvement.
- Curated and co-hosted a leading-edge fashion-tech conference.

# 2020-02 - 2021-10

# Senior Creative Strategist and Consultant - Freelance

SHOWZ - a retail design agency powered by creators (remote)

Created a successful, future-oriented in-house agency strategy and vision: based on various industry insights, market development and trends, customer needs and clients' resources.

## Contact

Right to work in the UK



#### Address

Earl's Court Square SW5 9UH London, UK

#### Mobile

+44 7919 9787 56

#### E-mail

hello@marietheresriegler.com

## Skills

Problem solving

Excellent

Communication skills

Excellent

Presentation skills

Excellent

Training/mentoring

Excellent

Analytical skills

Excellent

Strategic development

Excellent

Research design, Data collection and User testing

Very Good

- Conducted research on the impact of COVID on business models and changes in consumer behaviour.
- Created retail and communication strategies focusing on customer activation.
- Continuously developed experiential ideas and strategies based on current and future trends.
- Authored a white paper on post-pandemic retail.

## 2019-10 - 2021-10

## Regional Manager UK – Project based

TAKEaWALK.in (London, United Kingdom) Curated neighbourhood guide – Retail, Hospitality

- Collected data using various research methods to broaden results and tailor regional strategy (Primary research: Surveys, industry interviews, observation, user and product testing | Secondary research: market analysis, competitor analysis, trend analysis).
- Created positioning and key messages to differentiate business solution and product in market through targeted communication, high-quality partnerships and curation processes as well as value-added services and pricing, based on market needs.
- Nurtured partnership development and client success.
- Developed go-to-market plans and facilitated internal organizational readiness.

#### 2019-07

## Instructor – Global Entrepreneurship Summer School

CIEE | Berlin, Germany

- Teaching students to develop an entrepreneurial mindset with design thinking & lean startup methods.
- Participants learnt the necessary steps to turn a business idea into reality, to conduct market research, create a sound business model and a compelling pitch deck.

#### 2015-10 - 2018-10

## Corporate Innovation Projects – UX and CX

TU Berlin, University of Twente, CareerFoundry (Germany, Netherlands)
Projects for Deutsche Bahn, Brown-Forman, Schindler Digital Business Ltd.,
One For All, CareerFoundry

- Planned and conducted hands-on user research (e.g. stakeholder interviews, surveys, card-sorting, in-person and remote usability testings).
- Collected requirements from end-customers and business partners for product upgrades, added features and new product development.
- Played an important role in client meetings and research to successfully identify and understand clients' challenges and pain points.
- Gathered and analyzed relevant user needs for different projects across industries.
- Used holistic insights and gathered data to develop user personas and respective customer experience journeys.
- Worked with leading-edge technologies (e.g. eye tracking) to conduct A/B testings.
- Conducted market, trend, and competitor analysis to compare product offerings to market standards.
- Designed wireframes and prototypes as well as respective ideations.

#### 2012-09 - 2014-09

#### Assistant Marketing and PR Manager

Department Store Quartier 206 (Berlin, Germany) – Luxury industry, Retail

- Developed insights on marketing campaigns to assess performance against goals.
- Leveraged industry trends and competitive analysis to improve customer relationship building and experience.
- Built and strengthened strategic relationships with brands, customers, creative agencies and leading media partners.
- Planned and directed promotional events to attract customers and increase sales.
- Managed creation of marketing copy, images, videos, emails and other collateral.
- Orchestrated new product launches to expand market share and increase brand awareness.
- Worked with marketing- and external PR teams to create, deploy and

## Software

MacOSX

Excellent

MS Office and Google Suite

Excellent

UX Research: SurveyMonkey, GoogleForms, Usability Hub,

Excellent

CRM Tools: Mailchimp, Omnisend, vtiger, Highrise, Salesforce

Very Good

Project Mgmt Tools: Mural, Miro, Streak, Asana, Slack, Trello,

Very Good

Google Analytics, Website Optimisation, SEO

Very Good

InVision, UXPin

Good

## Languages

English, German

Native

Spanish, French

Advanced

optimize effective campaigns for the store.

#### 2010-11 - 2012-08

## Fashion and Luxury Industry Projects

- "LOOK TO INSPIRE" (Blog) Founder and Freelance Fashion Editor.
- Diane von Furstenberg Showroom Paris (Organization, Styling, Visual Merchandising).
- Ralph Lauren DACH (Sales, Retail Analysis, Brand Analysis, Research).

## **Education**

#### 2018

## **User Experience Design Certification**

CareerFoundry

- UX Fundamentals, UX Immersion, UX Specialization
- User-Centered Thinking, Usability Analysis and User Personas
- Information Architecture
- Wireframing, Prototyping, User Flows and A/B Testing
- Google Analytics, Semantics, SEO

#### 2016-08 - 2018-01

#### **MBA**

University of Twente - The Netherlands

- Cum laude graduate
- Dissertation: Case Study: Business Models and Value Creation in the German Product Design Industry
- Majored in Innovation, Entrepreneurship and Strategy
- Continued education in Digital Marketing, AI, Research

#### 2015-10 - 2016-07

## MSc: Innovation Management and Entrepreneurship

Technical University Berlin - Germany

- Project work in Business Planning, User Experience, Strategy
- Coursework in Sustainable Innovation, Intellectual Property and Entrepreneurship
- Professional development completed in qualitative and quantitative research

## **Additional Activities**

- Certified YOGA TEACHER
- MENTOR @MentorMe

## **Publications**

White paper on "Post-Pandemic Retail", 2020

Case study contributions in the following books:

"Global Marketing Strategy: An Executive Digest", 2016

"Ethics in Marketing: International Cases and Perspectives", Routledge, 2012

# Selected Research and UX/CX Projects

#### Website Content Audit for a division of a global logistics company

Website analysis, review and interpretation of website analytics, usability testings of 2 key processes, identification of weaknesses in the user journey, key messaging and content review of 4 competitors' websites, summary and prioritization of key findings and actionable recommendations for the client to improve usability and online customer journey for B2B clients

## Product Design of a Task Management App

Data analysis and interpretation using primary and secondary data, conceptual idea evaluation, research design (interviews and online survey), user testings, creating wireframes and low-fidelity prototypes, developing user personas and customer journeys

# Corporate Innovation Project with Deutsche Bahn: Digital business models and strategies in the mobility sector – Recommendations for improving the DB Navigator for business travellers

Research design, qualitative and quantitative research (survey and user interviews), market overview and defining benchmark criteria, evaluation of DB Navigator and comparison with selected apps, development of actionable recommendations and presentation of results

## (Digital), User-Centric Sales Strategy for a company in the spirits sector

Market and company specific research, conceptual idea evaluation, research design, qualitative interviews, data analysis and interpretation, developing 3 personas, developing different strategic concepts and recommendations and presentation of results

Research Project on: Challenges and recommended action steps when co-operating with start-ups for Schindler Digital Business Ltd.

Market and company specific research (technologies, company set-up, goals), developing a semi-structured interview questionnaire, scouting relevant tech start-ups, conducting interviews with both parties, identifying potential challenges and opportunities for the business, developing Do's and Don'ts as well as providing the company with a recommended future process model